<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The preparative for London. Be mercifull to your selves. An hearty and friendly premonition to the City of London, before their meeting in a Common-Hall, which is now to be called, by the good providence of God, upon Saturday the 24. June. VVhereby they have, if they neglect it not, a gracious opportunity offered them to become the happy instruments of their owne safety, and the peace and preservation of these kingdoms. / By Thomas Warmestry. D. D.</title>
            <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E449_26</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E449[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The preparative for London. Be mercifull to your selves. An hearty and friendly premonition to the City of London, before their meeting in a Common-Hall, which is now to be called, by the good providence of God, upon Saturday the 24. June. VVhereby they have, if they neglect it not, a gracious opportunity offered them to become the happy instruments of their owne safety, and the peace and preservation of these kingdoms. / By Thomas Warmestry. D. D.</title>
                  <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PREPARATIVE FOR <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be mercifull to your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An hearty and friendly premonition to the City of <hi>London,</hi> before their meeting in a <hi>Common-Hall,</hi> which is now to be called, by the good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, upon <hi>Saturday</hi> the 24. of <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhereby they have, if they neglect it not, a gracious opportunity offered them to become the happy inſtruments of their owne ſafety, and the peace and preſervation of theſe Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Warmeſtry.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 5.9.</bibl> 
               <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161869:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161869:2"/>
            <head>The Preparative for London.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SHall the Sword devoure for ever?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.26.</note> 
               <hi>Know ye not that it will be bitterneſſe in the latter end? How long ſhall it be then, ere ye bid the people return from following their brethren?</hi> Oh let me beſeech you to remember the Lord your God! And to take the waſted and bleeding condition of your poor diſtreſſed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into tender conſideation. Let the groanes and the ſighes of the fatherleſſe and the widdowes, and the cries of the oppreſſed and conſumed people of this Land; and of poor diſtreſſed <hi>Ireland,</hi> enter into your ears and pieree your hearts, that you bring not the guilt of innocent blood upon your ſelves. Provoke not the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to give you the dregs of that Cup, which hath been mingled in his fury againſt the ſinnes of you, and of theſe Nations; becauſe you have ſhewed no pitty upon your Brethren. Hear their cries unto you, that the Lord hear not their cries, and the cry of that bloud, that hath or ſhall be ſhed againſt you. And let it be in your hearts now at length to lay aſide all thoughts of diviſion and ſelf-ſeeking; of ſtrife and debate; of oppoſition and contention; And to put on bowels of mercy towards your fellow Chriſtians and Country-men. Yea, to be ſo mercifull unto your ſelves to prevent that impendent ruine &amp; deſolation that hangs over your City, like a flaming Sword or dreadfull Comet, and ſeemes every day to draw neerer and neerer unto you; leaſt when the fire is once kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led amongſt you, you cannot quench that with your fruitleſſe tears which you would not prevent by your timely endeavours.</p>
            <p>Conſider that power, that God of his great goodneſſe, of his great goodneſſe to you in ſpeciall, if you neglect it not, as well as to theſe Nations in generall, hath yet left remaining in your hands, and in your hands alone, with his bleſſing and aſſiſtance, which the Lord grant you, to put yet an happy period unto the great miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of theſe Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Conſider the great and manifold inducements, both heavenly and earthly, both politique and oeconomicall. Both publick and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161869:3"/>private, Both in point of duty, in point of piety, in point of juſtice and mercy, of honour, of intereſt, in the regards of ſafety, of wealth, of welfare; and of very being and ſubſiſtence, that do now exact it at your hands.</p>
            <p>It is the duty that nature in ſelf hath taught all men; even the very heathens themſelves, and is much more cleerly commended unto us by the rules of Chriſtian charity: That all men ought to ſeek the good of that ſtate and body of which themſelves are members. Piety commands us to ſeek the preſervation of Gods Church, and the recovery and eſtabliſhment of true Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. Juſtice engageth us to employ our lawfull and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian endeavours for reſtoring Law and Juſtice amongſt us, and of wronged and oppreſſed people unto their rights. Mercy obligeth us to ſeek the preſervation of our ſelves and brethren, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the farther ſhedding of innocent blood: That the poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this waſted Nation may be no longer worryed by thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage wolves and beares, that have now for ſo long a time take their pleaſure in the devouring of their brethren. If regards of honour be of any force with us, what an honour will it be unto this City to be the moderatours of ſo bloudy a quarrell, and to procure a reconciliation between the King and His people, which ſhall illuſtrate their names unto all poſterity, and endeare them to the hearts of the people, as the repairers of the breaches of their Country, and the preſervers of their King, and this whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome under God.</p>
            <p>If your intereſt, wealth, and welfare, or your very being and ſubſiſtence be conſiderable unto you: all theſe hang upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of peace, and upon the reſtitution of Government amongſt us; without this your forraign traffique is like to be obſtructed by the Navy; and if this fail you, the inteſtine trade is too ſhallow to feed the roots of ſo great a tree, as is this of your City. How many ſeverall callings, manufactures &amp; occupations, that make up a great, and the moſt flouriſhing part of your City will be utterly ſtarved in ſo great a ſtraite? Beſides that your trading at home doth daily, and is like, continually to decay, by the baniſhing of a great part of the people from the City; and by the impoveriſh-of many thouſands more, whereby they are diſabled, and others not ſuffered to exerciſe that commerce with you, that ſhould make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161869:3"/>for the mutuall ſupply and ſupportance of you and them; and ſo your very being is in queſtion, when your livelihood and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is cut off.</p>
            <p>Conſider the great and providentiall conjuncture of affaires in the preſent ſtate and condition of things, that doth invite you to the undertaking of this work.</p>
            <p>So great and conſiderable a part of the Kingdome, going before you with flaming deſires, in the proſecution of the deſigne of Peace: many whereof have opened the way unto you with their blood, and many more waiting and expecting your example and encouragement, no doubt, that they may joyn hands with you in ſo happy an undertaking.</p>
            <p>Conſider the charge that is like to be your part, if the Kingdom be engaged in another War.</p>
            <p>And the poor ſupplies that are likely to come in, in thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgments which you are already under, to enable you to nurce up ſuch a daughter of the horſe-leach, that wil ever be crying unto you <hi>give, give,</hi> without regard either to your neceſſities, or poſſibilities.</p>
            <q>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde habeas quaeret nemo, ſed oportet habere.</q>
            <p>When the Sword of the Souldier is once more made drunk with blond, you will finde much ado to make it underſtand reaſon.</p>
            <q>Non miſſura cutem niſi plena cruoris hirudo.</q>
            <p>Will they leave ſucking at your veines think you, till they have drawn out your very life, and heart blood?</p>
            <p>Conſider how bloudy and violent the proſecution, (you may gueſſe it by a late paroxiſme in <hi>Eſſex</hi>) how hazardous and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the event of another War will be; How you your ſelves are like to be divided within your ſelves, by the ſeveral parties which is likely to ſet you on fire amongſt your ſelves (&amp; that perhaps in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall ſenſe, when want and famine ſhall become the diſmall nurce of fury and rage amongſt you) at the beſt, it may expoſe you to a a City-war, and what confuſion is like to attend it?</p>
            <p>Conſider, if you could be chooſers of the ſucceſs, and in that you would not agree, but would be at war amongſt your ſelves, about the very event that you ſhould chooſe. But, in caſe you could, as the caſe now ſtands with you, that you have in either part, or in whole diſpleaſed all parties at one time or another: What event can you expect, that will not in probability make the ſpoile of your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161869:4"/>City, (if by that time you ſhall be extant, or have any thing left that is worth the plundring) the center of the motion, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and triumph of the victory?</p>
            <p>If the King prevaile; it's true, he is gracious, and hath learnt no doubt, by his own ſufferings, great leſſons of mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards others: But the ſons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> may be too hard for him, and perhaps he may have much adoe to conquer the rage of his incenſed Army, that he may be mercifull unto you.</p>
            <p>The Scots are hungry, The Army full of fury and offence, and when they are gotten into power, your cold courteſies will be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for injuries, what you have done will be forgotten, and what you have denyed, will be remembred. The Houſes have received diverſe diſcontents from you. The Presbyterian Party hath been deſerted by you, and many of them chaſed away, and others im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, by your admiſſion of the Army; you are a body made up of ſuch variety of complexions, and have ſhewed your ſelves ſo variable in your actions, That you have left room enough for every ſide to pick a quarrell, to make advantage of their power againſt you; and that Sword that ſhall be up, will hardly be diſputed with: each of them will finde their ſeverall enemies amongſt you, which may engage the whole unto diſaſter; or if they could finde none, yet it is no hard matter for arbitrary Conquerours to make enemies, that they may make uſe of their ſucceſſes. Though you be Guelph, yet your goods will be Gibellines.</p>
            <p>No way in the world to ſecure you in any degree, but a timely peace.</p>
            <p>Conſider the ſmall number of moments that is allowed you, for the diſpatch of this great buſineſſe, and the prevention of ſuch important miſchiefes, which calleth upon you to delay it no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; conſider the great and horrid impiety that is now diſcovered by the great mercy of God, in the deſigne to have poyſoned his Sacred Majeſty, which ſhould have been the crown of the reſt of thoſe helliſh cruelties, which have been exerciſed againſt Him; The God of Heaven look upon the authors and complices, and put it into your hearts to ſeparate your ſelves from all complyance with ſuch deviliſh and atheiſticall undertakers, and to ſeek the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Him out of their hands.</p>
            <p>Conſider, I beſeech you ſeriouſly to conſider, that happy opper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161869:4"/>which hath been heretofore denyed you, though many of you have deſired it: and now God by the forelaid plot of his Divine diſpoſition and goodneſſe, hath by the ſeaſonable returne and the courſe of times put into your hands, by the neceſſary pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like meeting of your City at this time, an opportunity which you ſhould looke upon as a call from heaven, to ſet you about this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed buſineſſe; an opportunity which if you now neglect, the Lord knowes whether ever you ſhall have the like againe: for ought you know it may be the laſt offer that ever God will make you, for the procurement of your own preſervation: for ought you know if you ſhall deſpiſe this mercifull conceſſion of the Lord unto you, before another ſuch a ſeaſon ſhall returne (and you know how hard it is to procure ſuch a meeting out of courſe.) The flame of your City may be the funerall pile of your ſelves, and your Wives and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and the Aſhes thereof may be left as the greate trophee, or monument of your ſtupid folly and impiety, and of the mine of this whole Nation: The Lord of his mercy give you wiſdome to prevent it.</p>
            <p>I know there are variety of opinions amongſt you: I know it too well, and I grieve to thinke on't. The Lord in his good time make an end of all differences; He is able to do it, and I hope he will do it, in ſome good meaſure, and in his good time, If we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint not our ſelves of ſo great a bleſſing: But in the mean time, I beſeech you let not any difference in judgement ſo quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the flame of Chriſtian Charity, which is a robe large enough to hide a multitude of errours, as well as fins: as to make us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all compaſſion unto one another; at leaſt not to forget to have compaſſion upon our ſelves; let us repaire the breaches in our affections, which I dare be bold to ſay, no diverſity of judgement whatſoever, hath Commiſſion from God utterly to diſſolve, &amp; then we may well hope that God will take his ſeaſon, to make up the differences that are in our apprehenſions: ſince it is his promiſe to the <hi>meeke</hi> that <hi>he will guide them in judgement. Pſal.</hi> 25.9. The unity of our hearts muſt be the foundation, to ſet up the building of our united judgements, for <hi>froward thoughts ſeparate from God, and wiſdome is a loving ſpirit,</hi> is canonicall truth, though it be in an Apocryphall booke. The want of mutuall love puts us out of the ſchool of Chriſt, ſince it is the very livery of his Diſciples <hi>to love one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161869:5"/>another, John</hi> 13.35. This is the right method of union, and I wiſh it were better thought on, and then the mutuall converſation, and peaceable and Chriſtian communion and conference with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, might be a great meanes to unite us in our judgements; but our Wars and fightings, come from our evill luſts. <hi>James</hi> 4.1. In the meane time do not henceforth hold your opinions at ſo deare a rate, as to make them the purchaſe of the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of your ſelves and theſe whole Kingdomes, and Nations. It is a truth wherein nothing can divide you, but inexcuſable, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with corruption: that you all ought to joyne the utmoſt of your force and wiſdome, to prevent ruine and deſtruction to that body whereof you are now Members, and the word of God layes no impediments in your way.</p>
            <p>If any carnall intereſts and ingagementſ do, I am ſure they are held at ſo high a price, by thoſe that ſtand upon them at this time, that if they underſtood it, they would not thinke it their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to maintaine ſuch intereſt.</p>
            <p>The aſſerting of private advantage, with the perdition of the publike, is as if a man ſhould pull a board out of the maine bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, to preſerve the beauty or integrity of a Cabin, which with all its ornament and entireneſſe, ſinkes unto the bottome in the drowning of the ſhip.</p>
            <p>The truth is, whatever the Articles be that are propoſed, there is inequality and injuſtice, in the very capitulation, whenſoever the publike is enforced to a treaty with private concernments for the preſerving of it ſelf: ſince no particular goods is at all conſiderable where it ſtands in counter to a publike, in the ſame or a higher kinde: And thoſe Members have rather need of evacuation then nouriſhment (that I ſay no more,) that like the ſpleene in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, maintaine their growth by the conſumption of the whole Body. The particular motions and inclinations of natural agents, maintaine themſelves in their utmoſt force, whilſt their currents run toward the. Ocean, and comply with the univerſall good. But as the Tide of the Sea carries back the Rivers, ſo when theſe naturall agents receive a prohibition, or ſuperſedeas, from the ſuperiour Court of the generall ſafety. Then <hi>Xanthe retro prope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat verſae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recurrere lymphae— Incipiunt:</hi> —</p>
            <q>
               <l>Then thoſe ſtreames do looſe their force,</l>
               <l>And do retreat from wonted courſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161869:5"/>
The particular element of water will forget its fluidity, and without any bonds of a froſt or ice; will be conſiſtent as waxe to preſerve the integrity of the univerſe; and upon the ſame termes it wil remove its deſcenſive motion, &amp; aſcend upward; and the ayre will take leave of its lightneſs and deſcend down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for the prevention of a <hi>vacuum,</hi> offering the tribute of their ſingle natures, as it were an homage due unto the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſupportance of the whole Body of the world. This is the Policy that God hath ſet up in the creatures; The whole world is a great Corporation, and this is the great and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable law whereunto God hath engaged all the parts of that Body, which is the great ligament of the entireneſſe thereof, and keeps out ſchiſme from that great Congregation. There is a publike ſpirit, I was about to ſay, a kinde of ſpirit of naturall martyredome, and ſelf-denyall, that runs through all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of this great fabrique, that makes each parcell thereof ready to ſacrifice it ſelfe, its appetite, its force, its kind of life, its very being, unto the ſafeguard of the totall compact; men I am ſure ſhould be of an higher ſchoole. The Philoſopher tells us man is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A politique living creature, not made then for himſelfe, but for publike Benefit.</p>
            <p>God hath ordained the good of mankind to hang as it were upon the ſocietie of mankind, and hath forbidden man to be happy alone, that he might engage him to ſeek after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſecuritie.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is, we may well conceive, that God hath made him the moſt inermous of all the creatures, and the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous of all the creatures almoſt: That the very love of himſelfe might bind him to love the publike before himſelfe, as it were, as without whoſe felicity himſelfe would be but a kind of damage and burden to himſelf. This as dark as it was in the now defaced records of nature, yet it was legible enough un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very heathens and produced theſe ſavings among them, <hi>Homo ſum &amp; nihil humanum à me alienum puto;</hi> I am a man, and reckon my ſelfe to be no ſtranger unto any thing within the bounds of humanity.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Dulce &amp; decorum eſt pro patria mori;</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:161869:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sweet is the damage, though't be great; yea 'tis a noble gain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To part with life, that Countries good thereby we may maintain.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>And anſwerable to theſe ſayings was the practice of many of them, as you may reade in the ſtories of thoſe heathen <hi>Heroes, Curtius, Regulus,</hi> and others; which however it was perhaps ſophiſticated with vain-glory, and came ſhort of the true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of genuine and native vertue, for want of the inward ſoule and life of it, and of the true guide, which is the knowledge of the true God, yet they may ſhame too many that pretend to have better eyes about them.</p>
            <p>Chriſtianity is the repairer, and purifier of that corrupt and droſſie humanity which we have received from our degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Anceſtours. This refines mankind again, and ſets us higher than the meere pitch of humane affection. It doth clear and rectifie this publike ſpirit; files it, and fourbiſheth it from the droſs of vain-glory, and eſtabliſheth it firm upon the right foundation; it doth ſet again the diſ-joynted bones of humane ſocietie which were broken and diſlocated by the fell of <hi>Adam,</hi> and faſtens them together with a ſtronger liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than mean humane regards, even with that great ſinew of Chriſtian charity. This teacheth us that we are all fellow-members of one another, and that therefore, as the particular members will diſpenſe with their private good, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and preſervation of the whole; ſo ought we to behave cur ſelves in the body of the Church and State. The Gangrened member refuſeth not to be cut off, that it may ſecure the life of the reſt of the frame: The arme will not my its own integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by expoſing the head unto a mortall blow, but will inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſelfe, to receive that wound which might otherwiſe be the deſtruction of all, by the maime of a more noble part, upon whole entireneſſe and ſafety, the ſafety and welfare of the whole fabrique doth depend. And to this purpoſe are thoſe ſacred lawes of the Chriſtian Common-wealth, binding us to account <hi>every man our neighbour to love our neighbour as our ſelves,</hi> which leaves no roome for a meere private affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but breakes open all encloſures from about the heart of a Chriſtian, and makes is to be of a publike intereſt; teacheth us
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161869:6"/>
               <hi>that no man ought to ſeeke his owne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>but every man a wealth;</hi> to have our prayers in common; <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven, &amp;c.</hi> our wealth in common, though not in Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſence, not to the deſtruction of propriety, but the Chriſtian diſpoſing of it; <hi>He that hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother have need, and ſhutteth up his compaſsion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi> nay to hold our lives in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon too, we <hi>ought to lay downe our lives for the brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16.</note> A true Chriſtian is to reckon of himſelfe, and of his life, and of all his riches, commodities, and advantages, as none of his owne, but the publick intereſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19</note> 
               <hi>Yee are not your owne</hi> (faith the Apoſtle) <hi>for you are bought with a price.</hi> If we had any right in our ſelves, any private right, Chriſt hath bought it, and hath given it as it were unto the Church, and to the publicke, unto pious uſes for the benefit of all. A true Chriſtian is the beſt Politician in the world, And <hi>Chriſts common-wealth is far better than</hi> Platoes.</p>
            <p>And is it not ſtrange then that againſt all theſe rules of nature, of humanity, and of Chriſtianity, men that would be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians, and the chiefe and only Chriſtians, ſhould yet ſtand upon their private concernments and advantages, where the ruine of a whole City, of a whole Church and Kingdom, nay, of three Kingdoms is in the queſtion? to ſecure themſelvs from thoſe loſſes which they have wilfully, that I ſay not wickedly expoſed themſelves unto, by the hazard of a totall deſtruction, and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation? That they ſhould employ their wits to interrupt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay thoſe ſeaſonable remedies, which the pious and Chriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of ſo many in your Citie have through the goodneſſe of God ſet their hearts upon, together with ſo great a part of the whole Kingdome for the recovery of peace, and the prevention of a totall and incurable deſolation ready to fall upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs and al the people of theſe nations? only to ſecure unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſome unwarrantable Bargains and purchaſes, that they have made with a flaming coale at the end of them apt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and waſt all the reſt of their poſſeſsions? or to make the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood of their brethren, the ſecurity of thoſe debts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the publick faith is engaged unto them? Let me beſeech them to be better minded, leſt it diſcover unto all the world that they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161869:7"/>are but uſurpers of that holy title of Saints &amp; Chriſtians which they take upon them; when all is done, he is the Chriſtian that walkes according to the rules of Chriſtianity; and that is, to be a publick man, and not to buy our wealth with the deſtruction of mens lives; and yet I have two queſtions to propoſe unto them, The firſt, whether when they have made all their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions ſure, whereby the work of peace is ſo induſtriouſly intercepted by them, they can tell how to free themſelves from as much, or a greater hazard of fayling in thoſe their ſelfe-ends that they aime at, than if they ſhould commit them to the calm gales of peace; or whether their deſignes are clearly ſetled upon ſo found and unfaileable a botom, that it is not poſsible that they and their hopes may ſinke in thoſe ſurges which they intend to hold up; ſince they have not all the winds nor the tides at their command, and thoſe that they thinke they have moſt on their ſide, and in their power, may when they leaſt dreame of it ſplit them upon the Rocks? They may remember that every Guſt that they have ſayled with, hath not brought them faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>My ſecond <hi>Quaere</hi> is, if they ſhould be ſo much maſters of their deſires, as to find a Haven unto themſelves in every ſtorme that they ſhall nouriſh, or yet farther raiſe upon this poore tottered vessell; whether all their gaine would countervaile the damage, or that with all that they ſhall get thereby they ſhall be able to make ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God, for one of thoſe many lives that ſhould be loſt in that turbulent adventure that they ſhall yet farther ingage in, or for one the ſmalleſt drop of that ſea of blood that by their meanes ſhall yet againe overwhelme this poore ſelfe-deſerted Kingdome? If they cannot tell how to anſwer theſe queſtions, I am fully aſſured they will be much more unable to anſwer ſome others that may be askt them at the day of judgement. But though golden Aſſes have long eares, yet they are commonly very dull of hearing. But I hope this paper may find a more eaſie paſſage unto the hearts of thoſe unto whom this is directed. If it ſhould be otherwiſe, yet I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire not of a remedy, whilſt I have ſo faire a promiſe from ſo many good affections, that have ſhewed themſelves amorous of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161869:7"/>the peace of this Kingdome, in this Citie, ſeconded with the happy preſage of ſo generall a concurrence of the ſeverall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where they are not countermanded by the force of oppoſites. And though it may put both you and them unto ſome coſt, yet the deareſt purchaſe that ſhall be made of peace, as it is a farre better Merchandize, in all probability, will be as eaſily bought, as another warre is likely to be maintained, though all the blood that is to be ſpilt ſhould be left out of the reckoning, and the layings out will have a farre more pleaſant returne.</p>
            <p>This buſines is mainely yours, and now it is as it were put into your hands, if you let it goe you let looſe a whole flood of miſchiefes, an ocean and deluge of calamities upon your ſelves and countrey. This poore weakned Kingdome is now falling into a relapſe, and that may be as dangerous to the body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick as to the naturall. The diſeaſe indeed was never perfectly cured, and now it is broken forth againe upon us, and the bloody iſſue runs afreſh amongſt us; and ſeemes to be like a raging fit after a troubleſome and unquiet ſlumber, which without a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy may be the Prodromus of death; you if any under Heaven may be the Phyſicians with Gods bleſsing to reſiſt the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of thoſe recoyling evils. That you may doe it, give mee leave here humbly to offer my poore advice, not to preſcribe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your judgements, but to ſubmit it to the corrections of ſuch better thoughts, which the Lord ſhall ſuggeſt unto your reaſons; if they prove not as wife as they are honeſt and hearty, yet the very folly and failings in them, may perhaps adminiſter unto you better apprehenſions; many good things are brought ſometimes into our thoughts by thoſe errors of other men, which we are engaged to correct.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God may be in the whole buſineſſe, let me deſire you to apply your ſelves unto him by earneſt prayer and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, for his ſpeciall influence upon you in theſe your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, for which purpoſe you have a mite offered into your treaſuryes in a forme of prayer ſet forth for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let nothing prevaile with you to relinguiſh the benefit of a Common-hall which is now due unto you of courſe, if I miſtake not, &amp; is ſo needful, &amp; of ſo great moment at this time,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161869:8"/>as you have bin well adviſed by another hand, which together with the ſenſe of your great concernment therein, may I hope ſave me the labour of preſſing it upon you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That in the next place (as that which muſt give life and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to all your reſolutions,) You deſire the liberty of ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy addreſſe unto his Majeſty, to be made by ſome of thoſe whole wiſedome and moderation ſhall preſent them to you as the fitteſt for ſuch an employment, that you may both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate your reſolutions unto him, and receive his appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of them, which will no doubt remove many feares and ſcruples, which are in the hearts of ſome among you, by ſuch ample ſatisfaction, which his meekeneſſe and mercy, and the longing deſire that lives in him after the good of you and all the reſt of his good Subject, would its like long agoe have given you, had he not bin deprived of the freedome of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of himſelfe unto you; and that his Majeſty may come to Hampton Court or ſome other place neere your City, to that end, and that he may have a Perſonall Treaty with the Houſes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſome courſe may be thought on, with his Majeſties conſent by the joynt concurrence of the City and Kingdome, for the paying of the debts of the publike faith, and for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imburſing unto the purchaſers that money that they have layd out in the purchaſe of Biſhops-Lands, or of the Church Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, any other ſuch like; which may be done by the contiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a moderate exciſe, by the Cuſtomes of exportation and importation, and by a publike yearly contribution both of the Laity &amp; Clergy throughout the Kingdom; which will be much more eaſily undergon, &amp; much more willingly, by all good men, than that the whole Kingdome ſhould be ruined; or an happy peace and reconciliation obſtructed for want of it; it will be an honourable &amp; a Chriſtian purchaſe to buy the peace of our King and Nation though it is not ſo honourable in them that ſell it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That his Majeſty be deſired to grant a free and generall pardon unto all, with an act of perpetuall oblivion, and that an oath may be framed by act of Parliament, to be taken by all Members of ſuccedent Parliaments, never to revive the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory thereof, nor to call any paſſages of theſe times into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161869:8"/>with ſuch limitations and exceptions onely as ſhall be found extreamely neceſſary to the preſervation of the King and Kingdome, which pardon to have its full effect, as long as they ſhall not attempt any new diſturbances otherwiſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come voyd, &amp; the Lawes of the Kingdome to proceed againſt ſuch as ſhall be actors therein. And that there may be likewiſe an act of Parliament made for the utter aboliſhment of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious names, &amp; tearms of oppoſition, as Cavaliers, Malignants, Roundheads, Committee-men, &amp;c. Vnder ſome great penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that the mention thereof may neither preſerve nor revive the quarrells hereafter among us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That out of this pardon onely thoſe may be excepted that ſhall be found to have had an hand in that late horrid deſigne of poyſoning his Majeſty.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That there may be a ſet time appointed for the diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this preſent Parliament, after the granting of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid pardon, and the enacting of thoſe Lawes onely which ſhall be found neceſſary for the preſent peace; and that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty may engage himſelfe by ſuch engagements as may ſatisfy, to call another free Parliament within two months after the diſſolution of this.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That all Armies may be ſpeedily disbanded before the diſſolution of this preſent Parliament, with the payment of ſome competent portion of their Arreares. And that the Scots be deſired to returne, having ſuch ſatisfaction given them as may be reaſonably deſired; and that theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch like payments may be made by the publike charge.</p>
            <p n="9">That the Militia of the City may be placed in ſuch hands, as his Majeſty, the Parliament, &amp; the city, ſhal agree on for a time, untill the ſtreames maybe reduced to their former channells.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That immediately the Government of the Kingdome may be mannaged by the knowne Lawes of the Kingdome, and all illegall powers diſſolved, and all illegall proceedings made voyd; every man that is not diſſeized by legall courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſtored unto his owne poſſeſſions; And the Miniſtry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their livings; and that thoſe Miniſters that have left their owne livings, and taken others, may be reſtored to their own againe, upon engagement not to diſturbe the peace of the Church and Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:161869:9"/>
11. That the Government and ſervice of the Church may ſtand for the preſent as it is eſtabliſhed by law, witn ſuch liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty onely allowed unto thoſe that are otherwiſe minded as ſhall be found neceſſary, untill upon the calling of another Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch alterations ſhall be legally made, as ſhall ſtand with Gods glory, the Truth of his Word, and may conduce to the peace of this Church and Nation, allowing all that liberty to tender conſciences, that doe not encounter theſe.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That His Majeſty may be moved to engage himſelfe upon the beginning of the next Parliament, to call a Nationall Synod, conſiſting of a convenient number of the moderateſt ſpirits of all Parties, and that there may be an oath admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto them, againſt partiality, and ſiding, and all turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent deſignes, and that by a faire and free debate in this Synod, there may be a reconciliation of judgements attempted; Firſt by declaring their conſent in thoſe things wherein all agree, <hi>in terminis,</hi> Secondly, by aſſaying an union in thoſe things wherein the tearms are oppoſite, by a faire and charitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</p>
            <p>And if neither of theſe courſes can end the contentions, That it may be conſidered, whether the queſtions that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main are in the Concluſions of either part neceſſary to be ſtood upon, if not, that the queſtions themſelves may be aboliſhed and ſilenced.</p>
            <p>And, that where there remaineth any difference un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable in things neceſſary, The judgement of ſome learned and moderate forraigne Divines may be deſired.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, That his majeſty having given ſuch ſatisfaction to the deſires of all ſides as is neceſſary for the ſecurity of a well-grounded Peace; He may be reſtored to his royall power, and all his Revenue and ſtate; The Queen, Prince; and the Duke of Yorke, and the Lady called home, and received with honour and ſafety.</p>
            <p>And that all may be concluded with a generall humiliation to God firſt for our ſinnes;</p>
            <p>And then a generall Thankſ-giving for his mercies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
